<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Peter Licari</title>
<link>www.peterlicari.com/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="www.peterlicari.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.0.8</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Book Review: Theory and Reality</title>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <link>www.peterlicari.com/posts/theory-reality-book-review/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><em>Theory and Reality</em> is an ambitious book that aims to accessibly cover a large swath of historical and philosophical ground. In many ways, it lives up to that ambition, making it well worth the read. In other, important ways though, the book occasionally devolves into muddy paste, sometimes making a <em>re</em>-reading necessary to fully grok what’s been covered.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When I went to graduate school, my very first class was called “Scope and Epistemology”—or “Scope” for short. It was a rite of passage for all who entered UF’s political science PhD progam. Taught by the brilliant (and brilliantly kind) Larry Dodd, the course syllabus was often mistaken as one of its textbooks. The damn thing was 30 pages and outlined thousands of pages of books and articles, from Kuhn to Gleick to Mayr, Gattone, and even freaking Asimov, that meant to show us not only the diversity of practices in social science but the equally remarkable diversity of beliefs over just what the heck this thing called “science” actually is. It was a whirlwind tour of epistemology, philosophy, and sociology of science. (Predominantly <em>social</em> science given, ya know, it was a poli sci PhD program—but not <em>exclusively</em> so, much to the course’s benefit). I was not unfamiliar with either philosophy or epistemology (I was a hair’s breath away from double-majoring in philosophy in undergrad), but it was an intimidating program. We were quickly reassured by more advanced students that, no, we didn’t have to “read” all of it—at least not in the sense one would read things in undergrad (a time-honored advisory that I would oft repeat many times myself to newer students, furthering the tradition). I still own many of those books and refer back to a few when I feel the need. The course cemented my latent loves of philosophy, epistemology, and science into (what I’m sure to be) a lifelong fascination: one focused with not only <strong>practicing</strong> social science but also interrogating “what even is this thing we call (social) science?” in philosophical terms.</p>
<p>Many of us came to realize that the syllabus for Scope was less a contract of expectations and more a gift. That “whirlwind tour” was a synthesis of decades of epistemological tumult that Dodd had lived through first hand. And since the issues were far from settled, I feel like he was also giving us a preview into many of the ideas and controversies we would have to grapple with ourselves over the course of our scientific careers.</p>
<p>This love is what drove me to pick up <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Theory-Reality-Introduction-Philosophy-Foundations/dp/0226300633"><em>Theory and Reality</em> by Peter Godfrey-Smith (2003)</a> from Amazon’s Audible service. <sup>1</sup><em>Theory and Reality</em> is an ambitious book that aims to accessibly cover a large swath of historical and philosophical ground. In many ways, it lives up to that ambition. In other, important ways though, the book at times does feel like it devolves into, to use Godfrey-Smith’s own verbiage, a muddy paste. There were times where I would relisten to chapters (sometimes <strong>three times)</strong> just to make sure I fully understood what was covered. I feel like the book rewards this effort, but not everyone will want to exert it. Still, what it does well, it does <em>very well</em>—making this book well worth the read.</p>
<hr>
<p>At the outset, Godfrey-Smith expresses that his overarching aim in writing this book is to convey a history of the philosophy of science; specifically a history in two senses of the word. The first is a timelie of the predominating ideas of the discipline (as well as from adjacent fields such as sociology of science): How have we conceptualized this thing we call “science,” as well the actions (both idealized and actual) of its practitioners? The second is a narrative of how said ideas (and their progenitors) interacted with each other.</p>
<p>This is more or less what he manages to do in the first third of the book. The first two substantive chapters start with brief discussion of early 20th century empiricism and its major philosophical tenets and issues (e.g., the issues of induction and confirmation), shift into a chapter on Popper, two on Kuhn (or, rather, two primarily on <em>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</em>), a chapter on Lakatosh, Laudon, and Feyerabend (not apiece—<em>collectively</em>), a short chapter blitzing through the sociology of science in the middle third of the century, then a chapter on feminist contributions to the subject, before pivoting to naturalistic philosophy. He doesn’t do so as a impassive retrospective observer though; he frequently interjects the discussions with both critiques and endorsements to the material. This includes both those that are generally accepted in the field as well as some of his own—though his is admirably careful and forthright in which views fall into which category. He does have a tendency to be a bit dismissive of <em>some</em> ideas without motivating clear reasons why (and these instances are highlighted due to the equally discernible tendency for <em>other</em> objections to get more strenuous refutations), but his contributions, on balance, add rather than detract from the quality of the section.</p>
<p>The core argument of this first section can be crystalized as follows: The early-to-middle(late) century for philosophy of science was characterized by a schism between empiricists (e.g., positivits) and those . Both sides had incredibly novel and important insights, but both often proffered leads that turned out to be dead-ends—or overplayed their philosophical hands, cornering themselves into very strange positions (Popper’s articulation of corroboration and some sociologists’ assertion that the world is in fact <em>created</em> at a <strong>foundational</strong> level by the theories and paradigms of scientists<sup>2</sup>).</p>
<p>It’d be a lot of ground to cover even <em>without</em> the additional commentary. But Godfrey-Smith manages to do so at a high average quality, albeit with noticeable variation. Perhaps it owes to my experience in Scope and in my undergraduate coursework prior to grad school, but I found it pretty easy to follow-along with the first few chapters—and I found the most of the interjections to be illuminating. (I especially liked his approach to the Black-Raven, White-Shoe issue in accounting inductive evidence—especially the version detailed late in the book when he discusses evidence). He was at his best when he dedicated his time to discussing narrower philosophical issues or the contributions of individual philosophers. The chapters on evidence, Popper, Kuhn, and the ensuing Lakatosh-Laudon-Feyerabend lightening round were some of the best in the book. Where things got less good (though not necessarily “bad”, for my view) is when he tried to cover entire <em>fields</em> in singular chapters. The Sociology of Science and Feminism chapters were among those aforementioned thrice-listens. I initially thought that it was because I was unfamiliar with the material, then I thought it was because I just wasn’t grokking it; but on the final time I realized that he was simply moving <em>way too fucking fast</em>. I sympathize with the challenge of distilling such large amounts of work into such a a condensed space—but considering he made <strong>two</strong> chapters out of Kuhn alone, it seems like a self-inflected wound with an obvious remedy: Split it out into a couple more chapters.</p>
<p>If history was Godfrey-Smith’s sole aim, the book could have been cut here. But that ultimately isn’t his full intention. The second aim of the book is to discuss the contemporary paradigms (or perhaps I should say “research traditions”) that dominated philosophy of science at the writing of his book—and they largely continue to hold sway today. The final aim is his advancing his own solutions to the core problems he identifies in the second part—though they all have roots in the discussions predominating the first. Throughout the book, he refers to these aims as “thirds” of the book—but, in reality, it’s more like history takes up the first 45% of the book before pivoting to</p>
<p>The chapter discussing naturalism more or less coincides with the transition into this pivot. Naturalism’s uptake comes nearer the end of the 20th century; but so do the other new agendas and perspectives that he focuses on. So he more or less abandons the chronological approach he took with the first section (though this doesn’t come as a surprise; he announces it as it happens). The chapters to come tackle “naturalistic” philosophies broadly, first on its own terms and then with regards to the “social structure of science;” It then pivots to “scientific realism”, a chapter on “explanation”, one on Bayesianism and evidence, and then one trying to harmonize the differences between empiricism, naturalism, and scientific realism. In this chapter, he retells the story of a reviewer warning that this final chapter has the potential to devolve into a “muddy paste.” As you might be able to guess from my use of the phrase earlier, it’s a critique that I largely agree with.</p>
<p>But the thing about paste, muddy or otherwise, is that it’s still pretty sticky. So while the concepts tended to blur together here<sup>3</sup>, the chapters does a pretty good job at having you stick around. This was some of the most engrossing material in the book, and I found my head moving quite vigorously at different parts of the book. It was mostly vertical when talking about how the aim of science is to use different “representational vehicles” (some linguistic, some mathematical, some visual, some computationally simulated, etc.) to provide an accurate representation of phenomena and relations observed in the real world—and when defending the broader tendency of science to invoke heretofore unobservable structures as part of a broader aim to explain what happens in the world. It did shake in the other direction when discussing Bayesianism because, at times, the approach appeared too glib and dismissive (such as the odd treatment of “Dutch books” and the thin objection to it on the grounds that some people may be averse to gambling)<sup>4</sup>. And I definitely found myself agreeing with the general conclusion to the book: That science is both an individual exercise and a social one. That scientists do aim to model the real world and that it is possible (and indeed advisable) to conditionally accept inductive arguments that have survived repeated testing with risky procedures. But also that scientists are engaged in a foundationally social enterprise and that we can only best understand their work (and the philosophy of science as well) as being influenced (and at times, constrained) by these social forces.</p>
<hr>
<p>All in all, I think <em>Theory and Reality</em> accomplishes what it sets out to do, though with varying degrees of clarity and persuasiveness. What it does well, it does <em>very</em> well—and there are moments where it manages to do exactly that throughout the whole book. But those moments are more heavily concentrated in the first half and in the concluding segments of a few of the final chapters; these successes, and their asymmetric spread, also serves to more severely accentuate the places where it <em>doesn’t</em> do as well. Places where the positions either expressed or taken weren’t as clear. Places where it felt too rushed to do such a large chapter-topic justice.</p>
<p>But I believe that this book is well deserving of a read by those interested in the philosophy of science broadly. It is a good survey of many ideas in the field, it incorporates and takes seriously competing intellectual programs that don’t often get coverage in other locations (i.e., feminist epistemology and critiques of science), and offers persuasive accounts for what scientists do, how, and why. Indeed, when I finished the book my first main feeling was sadness. Not because it was bad (because it was quite good), not because it was over (because it’s hard for <em>any</em> philosophy book to be <strong>that</strong> good) but because, just this last year, Larry Dodd retired from his position at UF. I was sad because this would have been a perfect addition to the Scope syllabus had he still been teaching it. But it has inspired me to keep better track of books like these so that, maybe someday, I’ll also be able to offer interested folks a suite of books that track the evolution of knowledge (both what we know and <em>how we know</em>) over my own career. I think it speaks very highly of this work that I think it has the potential to assist in cementing in others the same love of philosophy, science, and philosophy of science that Scope did for me.</p>
<p>Though, if I ever get the chance, I promise that I’ll do my best to stay shy of 30-something pages<sup>5</sup>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>The age of the book may discourage some from picking it up. Honestly, though, I didn’t even know it was this old as I was reading it.. It honestly reads more like a book from the time of its release onto Audible (2017) than from nearly two decades prior. I’m not sure if that is a comment of Godfrey-Smith’s perspicaciousness as a writer (and his ability to distill arguments into their more “timeless” elements) or on the rate of change in the discussed fields. To take a page from his book—literally—it’s probably something in between.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Though I did at times wonder if he was taking this argument a bit too far and, consequently, sparring with its straw man. I think he has a fair critique when he observes that theories and frames can strongly influence what we see but that their strength is fundamentally constrained by a shared external reality.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I feel like a lot of the differences between contemporary empiricism, naturalism, and scientific realism tend to either be real but highly technical or largely imagined but wielded fiercely by invested practitioners. In either case, largely inconsequential for the lay reader.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>For the curious, this could be articulated quite easily as someone merely having a larger degree of faith in the continuation of the status quo and in greater expressed uncertainties in alternatives to it.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>I solemnly swear: 25 pages max.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{licari2022,
  author = {Peter Licari and Peter Licari},
  title = {Book {Review:} {Theory} and {Reality}},
  date = {2022-11-07},
  url = {www.peterlicari.com/posts/theory-reality-book-review},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-licari2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Peter Licari, and Peter Licari. 2022. <span>“Book Review: Theory and
Reality.”</span> November 7, 2022. <a href="https://www.peterlicari.com/posts/theory-reality-book-review">www.peterlicari.com/posts/theory-reality-book-review</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>review</category>
  <guid>www.peterlicari.com/posts/theory-reality-book-review/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.peterlicari.com/posts/theory-reality-book-review/images/book_cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Thoughts on the 2020 Election</title>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <link>www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I thought I would post my prediction for the election and a few thoughts regarding it more generally. I’ll be peppering in some maps that I’ve made to help illustrate my general thought process.</p>
<section id="when-can-we-expect-all-this-to-wrap-up" class="level1">
<h1>When can we expect all this to wrap-up?</h1>
<p>First and foremost, there’s a chance that we’ll know, with a reasonable degree of certainty, who the winner of the electoral college vote will be by about 9 PM. That chance goes up if we push the deadline ’till 1 AM. But there’s also a solid chance that we won’t know for a few days to a week. Honestly, I’m not comfortable betting on which I think will happen.</p>
<p>Just so we’re all on the same page: That doesn’t mean there’s a snowball’s chance in Hell that we’ll know the vote <em>totals</em> by the end of the night. We never actually know the totals for all of the states by the time election night bleeds into national political hangover day. Many states (like Alaska and California) are notoriously slow with counting their ballots–and the vast majority of other states spend a few days curing problematic ballots and/or allowing ballots post-marked prior to Election day to filter in. (Military votes are in a similar situation.) We won’t see validated totals for weeks after.</p>
<p>That’s how it is with <strong>every</strong> election. However, in normal times, we’ve gotten pretty good at using a combination of exit-polls and vote totals scraped from state/county election officials’ sites to <em>project</em> the eventual winner.</p>
<p>As you might have recognized, we are not in normal times.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-the-hold-up." class="level1">
<h1>What’s the hold-up.</h1>
<p>In a word: Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>Through a combination of COVID-19 and general anxiety/enthusiasm catalyzed by the last four years of President Trump’s tenure, we saw mind-bogglingly high levels of early/mail-in voting. At least <strong>100 <em>million</em></strong> people voted early this year, according to estimates from <a href="https://twitter.com/ElectProject/status/1323663599697539074?s=20">Michael McDonald’s US Elections Project</a>. That translates to 73% of the nation’s 2016 vote total. Some states surpassed their 2016 totals.</p>
<p>However, not all states have laws that allow them to tabulate early ballots as they come in. This map from Pew Research shows which states tabulate the votes as they come in.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/AbsenteeBallots.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</center>
<p>The state throwing the biggest monkey-wrench into the works is undoubtedly Pennsylvania. For reasons that I’ll get to in a second, Pennsylvania is critical to President Trump’s pathway to victory. Without it, he has very little chance of making it into office. Complicating things more is that Pennsylvania counts day-of votes <em>first</em> before the early vote. It could take days before the early vote totals are cleared. And given that Joe Biden appears to be leading quite dramatically among early voters, <a href="https://twitter.com/Politics_Polls/status/1320698523030032384?s=20">according to the polls</a>, there is a solid chance that President Trump will appear to be leading in the state by the end of the night. If Joe Biden is winning PA by sunrise tomorrow—barring any irregularities in the day-of counting or insanely long lines—then he’s most likely won the election. (Even with the curse of daylight savings pushing daybreak an hour earlier.)</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-see-the-election-turning-out" class="level1">
<h1>How Do I See the Election Turning Out?</h1>
<p>Here is what I see as the most likely outcome when everything is said and done. (From here on out, I’ll largely be using maps I’ve generated <em>via</em> <a href="https://www.270towin.com/">270 to Win</a>.)</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/likelyoutcome.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>I should caution that by “most likely”, I mean that I think this has somewhere between a 20-30% chance of it happening. There’s a better chance than not that I’m gonna be wrong—so don’t set your clock to it.</p>
<p>(Another daylight savings joke. I’m still not over it. Now that I’m a father to a newborn, I can’t even begin to fathom how <em>my</em> parents managed this BS.)</p>
<p>Many of these states are seen as toss-ups: Texas, Florida, North Carolina, Georgia, and Arizona. I settled on the answers that I did largely by taking these states, case-by-case, and thinking about how they performed over the last few elections, including 2018 and 2016, and their current political momentum. Here’s an abbreviated look at my rationale:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Arizona:</strong> Long-term trend towards purple, favoring Red; generally unfavorable to Trump and Trumpism in particular; 2018 strong showing for Democrats + strong polling.</li>
<li><strong>Florida:</strong> Purple for a long time; recent history of Blue on Presidential races; super tight midterm.</li>
<li><strong>Georgia:</strong> Solid red in Presidential contests; maintained Red in midterms; getting closer but still a red state in the south.</li>
<li><strong>Iowa:</strong> Swingy the last couple decades, but a consistent polling lead for Trump.</li>
<li><strong>Maine-2:</strong> Generally weak right as is; fairly large disdain for Trumpism; consistent Biden Lead (albeit small).</li>
<li><strong>Nebraska-2:</strong> Consistent polling lead for Biden.</li>
<li><strong>North Carolina:</strong> Swingy; solid 2018 performance; consistent advantage for Biden in Polling</li>
<li><strong>Ohio:</strong> The supposed king-maker. Consistent Trump advantage in the polling; solid Republican performance in 2018.</li>
<li><strong>Texas:</strong> Gradual demographic transition to purple accelerated by Trump. It’d be bat-💩 crazy if it went from stalwart Red to true purple within a single cycle.</li>
</ul>
<section id="which-states-im-most-likely-to-be-wrong-about." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="which-states-im-most-likely-to-be-wrong-about.">Which states I’m most likely to be wrong about.</h2>
<p>The states I’m most likely to get wrong are probably Georgia, North Carolina, Florida, and Maine-2. I think Maine-2 will be a decent indicator of how well the GOP’s senate chances will fair though; if that goes Blue, Collins is probably toast and any hopes that incumbents will be insulated from down-ballot effects stemming from Trump most likely go out the window. I’m less bullish on the senate flipping than others, but that will be a fair indicator of a bad night for the GOP all around.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="biden-pathways-to-victory" class="level1">
<h1>Biden Pathways to victory</h1>
<section id="biden-has-a-strong-wall" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biden-has-a-strong-wall">Biden has a strong wall</h2>
<p>The reason I’m as bullish as I am for Biden (besides the appeal of the alliteration) is that the current toss-ups can literally <strong>all</strong> break for President Trump and Biden would <em>still</em> win—provided there aren’t any major surprises in the polling.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/trumpwinsall.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>Not all of these states are equal with regards to the President’s chances. No state’s return is independent of the others—if Biden won Texas, that means we’re looking at a <em>bona fide</em> blue malestrom, let alone a wave—but some states give more information about how other states are going to break than others. <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/trump-biden-election-map/">FiveThirtyEight has a tool</a> that uses the correlations among polling errors to show how a victory in some states ripples out to signal what’s happening in others. A Trump win in Georgia doesn’t shift things much, nor does one in Texas, because frankly it’s a shock that they’re even in play. A win in Florida, however, drastically lowers Biden’s chances and suggests a map that looks like the one above. However, even in that case, the President is still <strong><em>not</em></strong> favored to win if only for the fact that Biden is still leading in the Electoral college.</p>
<section id="the-upshot-however-is-that-if-trump-loses-any-of-those-states-his-only-path-to-victory-lies-in-there-being-large-unprecedented-degrees-of-polling-error." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-upshot-however-is-that-if-trump-loses-any-of-those-states-his-only-path-to-victory-lies-in-there-being-large-unprecedented-degrees-of-polling-error.">The upshot however is that if Trump <em>loses</em> any of those states, his only path to victory lies in there being large, unprecedented degrees of polling error.</h4>
<p>I know, I know. Some of you might be thinking: <em>“But Peter! The polls in 2016…”</em> to which I will reply (for what I pray to all that is good and holy is the <strong>last time</strong>) that even the state level polls did <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-polls-are-all-right/">reasonably well in 2016</a> in the aggregate—and more pollsters have been doing more <em>high quality</em> state-level polls than last time. There have also been adjustments across the industry to account for the biggest systematic source of polling error in 2016, which was not properly accounting for Trump’s support among White, non-college educated voters.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="bidens-best-cases" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bidens-best-cases">Biden’s best case(s)</h2>
<p>The best case scenario for Biden is that he picks-up all of the toss-ups. But I should really emphasize that <strong>I don’t think this is a particularly likely outcome.</strong></p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/bidenlandslide.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>A more realistic “great day” scenario for Biden is that he wins picks up Florida, North Carolina, Arizona, and Georgia while Trump gets Texas, Ohio, and Iowa.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/bidenmorelikely.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>Judging from the correlations in polling errors, Florida will be a good (but not perfect) indicator of how Georgia and North Carolina go. (Georgia could be called first but that doesn’t necessarily mean that Florida will go with it; the leverage one state has over another is asymmetric. For example: North Carolina going red/blue means less for Texas’ eventual outcome than Texas going red/blue means for North Carolina.) Ohio will probably provide a good (but, again, <em>not perfect</em>) indication for how the other three states will break.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="trump-pathways-to-victory" class="level1">
<h1>Trump Pathways to victory</h1>
<section id="without-pennsylvania" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="without-pennsylvania">Without Pennsylvania</h2>
<p>Just because I expect the President to lose doesn’t mean I think his loss is <em>inevitable.</em> But it’s tough. Really tough. And it’s made all the tougher because he’s currently not favored in Pennsylvania. And by “not favored in Pennsylvania” I mean that <a href="https://projects.economist.com/us-2020-forecast/president/pennsylvania"><em>The Economist</em> is giving Biden a 95% chance of carrying the state</a>. Trump will have to outperform the polls by a strong margin to carry the day. The most likely states, given the margin of error for the most recent state level polls, is Nevada, New Hampshire, Maine-2 and Nebraska-2. That will give Trump 270 votes in the Electoral College.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/trumpnopa.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>But I want to stress how unlikely that is. Many of these wins are not all that correlated with each other—meaning that a win in any of them early on doesn’t necessarily portend a Biden defeat. (Other state combinations are also possible, but we’d be talking about even <em>less</em> likely polling errors.)</p>
</section>
<section id="with-pennsylvania" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="with-pennsylvania">With Pennsylvania</h2>
<p>A trump victory in Pennsylvania <em>dramatically</em> improves the President’s chances. If the President wins there, it’s likely that he’s winning in a lot of other places that he’s currently not favored. However,it should be noted that <em>even then</em> he’d still need to pick up every one of the toss-up states. That can be helped by the fact that winning Pennsylvania would suggest a large degree of errors in the polls. But that degree of error is, I have to emphasize, really improbable. This outcome isn’t necessarily <em>less</em> likely than the one above, but pulling-off Pennsylvania would be an incredible upset. And, honestly, I would probably need to seriously reevaluate my life choices should it happen: especially my chosen profession.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/trumpwithpa.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>The other point to consider when weighing out the importance of Pennsylvania is just how <strong>long</strong> that would make the contest. Basically, if Trump wins every toss-up state, then we’re not going to know the election’s outcome until about the end of the week <em>at earliest.</em> Because, as mentioned above, <em>Pennsylvania counts their early votes last and haven’t started counting them at all.</em> If Trump is ahead by the end of the night, we’ll just have to wait and see if the Biden advantage banked-up from early voting is enough. (Although, as a Floridian, I must confess that it’ll be nice to have all of the attention away from us for once.)</p>
<section id="in-short-in-order-for-the-president-to-win-hes-going-to-have-to-pull-off-one-helluva-upset.-that-doesnt-make-it-impossible-upsets-happen-all-the-time-but-by-definition-it-makes-it-unlikely." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-short-in-order-for-the-president-to-win-hes-going-to-have-to-pull-off-one-helluva-upset.-that-doesnt-make-it-impossible-upsets-happen-all-the-time-but-by-definition-it-makes-it-unlikely.">In short, in order for the President to win, he’s going to have to pull-off one helluva upset. That doesn’t make it impossible (upsets happen all the time) but, by definition, it makes it <em>unlikely.</em></h4>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="cool.-but-what-if-trump-doesnt-leave" class="level1">
<h1>Cool. But what if Trump doesn’t leave?</h1>
<p>I can understand the concern some have that Trump won’t leave given that, for the first time in American history, a President has repeatedly refused to commit to a peaceful transition of power. If he refuses to concede the election, we’ll be in an unprecedented situation in our country. (And, yes, I’m including <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1876_United_States_presidential_election">1876</a> because there wasn’t an incumbent involved with that colossal cluster f*ck.)</p>
<p>However, being unprecedented here at home doesn’t mean unprecedented abroad. The last few decades are unfortunately replete with examples of democratic states backsliding into either competitive or outright authoritarianism. And there are lessons to be learned there. Namely, a Trump coup is unlikely to be fruitful if he doesn’t have the support of key power brokers in the Government as well as in the Military. And I frankly don’t think Trump has that support.</p>
<p>When it comes to Congressional Republicans, while they certainly have acquiesced to large expanses in executive power—and excused a number of insane controversies—they have, to their credit, largely rebuked the President when he made suggestions that are unequivocally undemocratic (such as moving election day or not peacefully conceding an electoral loss.) McConnell’s support of the President seems to extend only as far as the latter been able to reliably install conservative judges into the federal judiciary. I’m <strong>not</strong> saying that we should sleep on the possibility that McConnell and the rest turn out to be entirely without scruples and little-d democratic principles. But I <strong>am</strong> saying that we shouldn’t necessarily buy-in to the idea that they’ll do such open, incontrovertibly authoritarian moves.</p>
<p>Additionally, Trump would need the support of the Military. Looking at how they responded to his attempts to deploy troops during the height of the protests earlier this year, I feel more confident saying that he doesn’t have it. <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2020-election/more-200-retired-generals-admirals-endorse-biden-including-some-who-n1240842">Additionally, 200 retired generals, including a few who served under Trump, endorsed Biden.</a> I’m not saying that this means the entire current membership of the higher brass does, too—but Trump’s support would need to be far more consolidated than it appears to be.</p>
<p>I think it’s quite likely that Trump will be a petulant child up until Joe Biden is sworn in. It would be, without a doubt, the most bonkers lame-duck period in modern American history. But I think that, if he loses the election, there’s a far better chance that he leaves than him fighting to stay.</p>
<p>(A more likely issue was/is Trump stealing the election. However, a number of important lower and Supreme Court decisions over the last few weeks—even those posed to conservative justices—have largely come back against the GOP plaintiffs. The President has been open about his hopes that the election will be close so that they can be litigated in the courts. But there seems to be a better chance that it’s not close enough for them to entertain all of the challenges he and his team have cooked up.)</p>
</section>
<section id="so-does-a-biden-win-mean-that-american-democracy-is-safe" class="level1">
<h1>So does a Biden win mean that American democracy is safe?</h1>
<p><em>ahahhahahahahhahahhahhahhaha</em></p>
<p>Oh.</p>
<p>Were you serious?</p>
<p><strong><em>ahahhahahahahahahahahahahahaah * laughs start breaking down into sobs *</em></strong></p>
<p>I think American democracy is in peril. I don’t think that’s necessarily a controversial position among those who study democratic regimes and how they degrade. But I don’t think that Joe Biden is going to single-handidly (or even jointly, with Kamala Harris and/or a unified Democratic government) save the country.</p>
<p>I’ll probably write (or record) more about this later so I won’t give it all away now: But we’re going to need to see governmental reforms the likes of which we haven’t seen since the post-Watergate Congress. We’re going to need that <em>and</em> a major overhaul in our media environment <em>and</em> strengthening of our critical institutions <strong>and</strong> a lot of elite coordination and cooperation across both sides of the political spectrum <strong><em>and</em></strong> a public shift in what conduct we do and don’t condone, see as civil and uncivil, as acceptable and unacceptable. None of it has to be resolved day one, or even within Biden’s tenure, but we need to make serious progress in these areas. There is no other option. Because our political momentum, in this current moment, does not bode well; our trajectory follows a well-worn path into authoritarianism and there are dispiriting few junctures remaining to veer off of it.</p>
<p>I don’t think it’s impossible. I am ever the optimist—if only for my own sanity. But the work has only just begun. And it must be done even if I’m wrong and Biden loses.</p>
<p>If I’m being honest, <em>especially</em> then.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{licari2020,
  author = {Peter Licari and Peter Licari},
  title = {Thoughts on the 2020 {Election}},
  date = {2020-11-05},
  url = {www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-licari2020" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Peter Licari, and Peter Licari. 2020. <span>“Thoughts on the 2020
Election.”</span> November 5, 2020. <a href="https://www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election">www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>elections</category>
  <category>reflection</category>
  <guid>www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.peterlicari.com/posts/thoughts-prior-2020-election/images/likelyoutcome.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="94" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to Do Unequal Randomization in Qualtrics Surveys</title>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <link>www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Recently, some coauthors and I were working on a survey experiment in Qualtrics where we were assigning people into 4 different groups. This is something that Qualtrics can do really easily with its in-built <a href="https://www.qualtrics.com/support/survey-platform/survey-module/survey-flow/standard-elements/randomizer/">randomizer</a> function. If you use this, and keep <a href="https://www.qualtrics.com/support/survey-platform/survey-module/survey-flow/standard-elements/randomizer/#EvenlyPresentElements">evenly present elements</a> on, your respondents will be sorted in roughly evenly. So if you have 16 respondents and 4 groups, on average you’ll get 4 people per group.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>But we had a different situation. We had four groups but we <strong>didn’t</strong> want it split evenly. We wanted it so that group 1 was half of the survey, and groups 2, 3, and 4 took up thirds of the remaining half.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>Unfortunately, Qualtrics doesn’t seem to have an option that let’s you select unequal probabilities natively. If you deselect “evenly present elements” it’ll just randomize without any real concern towards whether your groups end up looking roughly equal. But that’s not what we needed. So I wanted to write about our solution to this so, hopefully, others in a similar situation might be able to find a work-around that works for them, too!</p>
<p>Our solution used <strong>embedded data</strong>, <strong>then branches</strong>, and the standard <strong>randomizer.</strong> I’ll also talk about how you might be able to generalize this to any number of conditions (although some are more work than others).</p>
<section id="starting-with-embedded-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="starting-with-embedded-data">Starting with Embedded Data</h2>
<p>As you probably know: After you’re done with your Qualtrics survey, you can export it as a csv or as a xlsx file. In addition to the answers to your questions, it’ll also include some project and respondent metadata. But you can also program the survey for it to include you’re own custom metadata to be embedded in the project. You can do this by clicking on the “add new element here” button and adding embedded data to the project.</p>
<center>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/3.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
</center>
<p>Once you’ve done that, you can customize your field to have whatever name you want. You can also set the value for this field. Here I set a variable named “test” equal to the value “1”. When I export the results for this survey, there will be a new column called “test” where the value for every respondent will be 1.</p>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/4.PNG" class="img-fluid"> Importantly, though, you can also set multiple conditions for the embedded data field! You do this by clicking “add below” and adding more embedded data sections.</p>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/5.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Pop quiz! What would you get in the “test” column if you ran this survey as is?</strong></p>
<p>You’d get <strong>4</strong> because, right now, you’re telling Qualtrics:</p>
<ul>
<li>Invent a column called test. Set it equal to 1.</li>
<li>Actually, remember test? Set it to 2.</li>
<li>I lied. Make it 3 now.</li>
<li>Jk. 4.</li>
</ul>
<p>Here’s where we start using the randomizer.</p>
</section>
<section id="omg-so-random" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="omg-so-random">“OMG so random…”</h2>
<p>As it stands now, you’re going to end up with a field called test where the value is set to 3 for all respondents. Instead of that, we can use the randomizer to make it so that 1/4 of the sample has a value of 1 for test, 1/4 has a value of 2, 1/4 has a value of 3, and 1/4 has a value of 4.</p>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/6.PNG" class="img-fluid"> You may be thinking “Cool. But this doesn’t do anything for me. I’m right back at equal probabilities for my experimental conditions.” And you’d be right if we were stopping here.</p>
<p>But we’re not stopping here.</p>
<section id="were-going-to-nest-randomization-conditions." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="were-going-to-nest-randomization-conditions.">We’re going to <em>nest</em> randomization conditions.</h4>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/7.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This programming is pretty similar to what we ended up using. Let’s follow the logic of the flow:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Randomly pick either the test 1 condition with 50 % probability.</li>
<li>If it is not picked, then randomly select one of the remaining 3 conditions with 1/3 probability each.</li>
</ol>
<p>This will mean that half of the respondents will get test1 and 1/6th will go to each test2, test3, and test4. Which is what the situation is in the second image and exactly what we were looking for in the real-life scenario.</p>
<p>This nesting is the key thing here. <strong>By nesting your randomizers strategically, there are few combinations that you won’t be able to achieve.</strong> This sort of set up can be really useful if you’re doing a multifactorial survey experiment.</p>
<p>We can wrap this all up with a neat bow through some branching.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="branch-it-out" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="branch-it-out">Branch it out</h2>
<p>Now we can do some branches so that our participants only see the blocks that they’re intended to see. Then branches work off of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_algebra">boolean logic</a>. If a condition is <code>TRUE</code> then it’ll run a particular course of action. If it’s <code>FALSE</code> then it won’t run that action. In Qualtrics, you can set the branching logic so that it reflects the metadata that was assigned to participants through the randomizer.</p>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/8.PNG" class="img-fluid"> After that, you can add the block that you wanted people with test condition 1 (and only test condition 1) to see. And if you repeat it out, then you can complete the whole survey flow. Here’s basically what our survey looked like once the logic is completed all the way to the end.</p>
<p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/9.PNG" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>One of the things I really like about this approach (rather than, say, using a <a href="https://www.qualtrics.com/support/survey-platform/common-use-cases-rc/assigning-randomized-ids-to-respondents/">random number generator</a> and a bunch of then branches) is that this makes your later analysis pretty easy. If you’re making pivot tables, you can group off of that variable’s value. If you’re doing ANOVA in SPSS, Stata, or R, you’ve got a single variable already to go without having to do any post-hoc coding. It also makes it easier to set dummy variables if you do a more advanced regression analysis. I’m personally a big fan of doing small-to-moderate amounts of work up-front to save myself larger amounts of work down the road. I’m a big believer that work borrowed from your future self compounds with interest.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{licari2020,
  author = {Peter Licari and Peter Licari},
  title = {How to {Do} {Unequal} {Randomization} in {Qualtrics}
    {Surveys}},
  date = {2020-08-05},
  url = {www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-licari2020" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Peter Licari, and Peter Licari. 2020. <span>“How to Do Unequal
Randomization in Qualtrics Surveys.”</span> August 5, 2020. <a href="https://www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups">www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>surveys</category>
  <category>qualtrics</category>
  <category>research design</category>
  <guid>www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.peterlicari.com/posts/Qualtrics-random-groups/images/2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Surveying is a Beautifully Foolish Endeavor</title>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <link>www.peterlicari.com/posts/surveying-beautiful-endeavor/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I binged Hank Green’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Beautifully-Foolish-Endeavor-Novel-Carls/dp/152474347X"><em>A Beautifully Foolish Endeavor</em></a> yesterday and it is, let me tell you, just fantastic. I don’t plan on writing a longer review because I didn’t really write any notes. I didn’t <em>want</em> to take notes. Not because it was bad, but because I didn’t want to peel my eyes away from the page for the short seconds it’d take for me to grab my pen and notebook. I was too engrossed to want to do anything but live in its pages for however long it’d let me. So, no review—but maybe that ardor could stand in place of one.</p>
<p>But aside from just being human, well-written, and the right mix of cynical and optimistic, it is also just an eminently and endlessly quotable book. There are quotes here that I plan on using when I talk about machine learning in my upcoming data science class. Quotes that just stabbed me in the chest with self-recognition (<em>cough cough</em> Miranda being a workaholic <em>cough cough</em>). And then there are quotes that make me feel that Green is one of the few science fiction authors who actually understand the sociology and psychology of being a practicing scientist (which, ya know, <em>SciShow</em> and his M.S.—so it makes sense). But then there’s this quote near the end of the book that so perfectly described being a survey researcher that it made me laugh out loud:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>[We wanted to] dive deep into our survey responses. Except there were just too many…no matter how we filtered, there just wasn’t a good way.</strong></p>
<p><strong>April and I were griping about this around the black marble countertop in the kitchen when Carl came in and overheard us.</strong></p>
<p><strong>“Just do a search,” Carl said.</strong></p>
<p><strong>“The searches take forever and we don’t know what to search for,” April replied. “It’s just a bunch of dumb data. Most of the useful stuff is in text responses, which is impossible to parse.”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I loved and loathed the reductionism of “dumb data”—mostly because it’s right. Until we data geeks make the decisions on what to model, how to model it, and how to frame and embed our results into a digestable narrative, it is literally just that. Dumb data, (sometimes) intelligently collected. And also, it’s so, <strong>so</strong> spot-on to note that almost all of the really juicy stuff is in the open-ended responses where people just let you know what’s <em>actually</em> going on. Or at least their inwardly-biased interpretation of their messy cognitive processes—<strong>which is still super cool and really interesting!</strong></p>
<p>As an example: for my dissertation, I had completely written-off games like <em>Hearts</em> as sociopolitically unimportant until some respondent mentioned that there are online lobbies where people use the game to chat about politics. I never would’ve learned that if I didn’t bother to read what my respondents had taken the time to write. And there have been a few papers that make the point that we should really pay more attention to the nuance that people write in rather than (often incorrectly) discretizing them on the basis of hardline, <em>ex ante</em> coding rules.</p>
<p>I’m envious that April and Maya had an alien superintelligence to parse through all of that data and get to all the juicy bits. Sure we have NLP and algorithims for market segmentation—but do <em>they</em> come from a near-omniscient monkey? Didn’t think so.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{licari2020,
  author = {Peter Licari and Peter Licari},
  title = {Surveying Is a {Beautifully} {Foolish} {Endeavor}},
  date = {2020-08-03},
  url = {www.peterlicari.com/posts/surveying-beautiful-endeavor},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-licari2020" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Peter Licari, and Peter Licari. 2020. <span>“Surveying Is a Beautifully
Foolish Endeavor.”</span> August 3, 2020. <a href="https://www.peterlicari.com/posts/surveying-beautiful-endeavor">www.peterlicari.com/posts/surveying-beautiful-endeavor</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>review</category>
  <category>surveys</category>
  <category>fiction</category>
  <guid>www.peterlicari.com/posts/surveying-beautiful-endeavor/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Capturing a PowerPoint/Google Slides Lecture with Open Source Software</title>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Peter Licari</dc:creator>
  <link>www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>A number of schools are either <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/08/us/coronavirus-schools-san-francisco-seattle.html">shutting down</a> or <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/education/2020/03/09/princeton-requires-lectures-seminars-go-online-only-temporary-move-amid-covid-19-outbreak/">transitioning classes to an online format</a> due to the novel corona virus (also known as COVID-19). (UF just let us know Yesterday that, while it isn’t yet mandatory, <a href="https://www.wcjb.com/content/news/UF-Students-return-to-campus-after-Spring-Break-amidst-coronavirus-fears-568639131.html">we should start transitioning sooner rather than later</a>). This isn’t going to be an easy transition for a lot of us—students and faculty alike. Not everyone makes living on the Internet basically a second job. I’m planning on writing a workflow for my intended solution—hosting lectures live in a Discord server with password-protected Google Forms as attendance—in the next few days. But I know that many people are going to feel that simpler is better for them. I got this text from a good friend of mine yesterday as we were talking about it:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Can I just like…screen capture my computer while I’m presenting and just upload that?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Absolutely!</em> And it’s easy to do with some Open Source software. In fact, <strong>you can do it with whatever your presentation software of choice (PowerPoint, Google Slides, LibreOffice, Beamer, etc.).</strong> This is especially helpful because, while PowerPoint offers an easy recording option, the same can’t be said for everything. So, for this post, I’m going to walk y’all through how to use OBS to record yourself giving a PowerPoint presentation so you can upload it to your students.</p>
<section id="contents" class="level1">
<h1><strong><em>Contents</em></strong></h1>
<ul>
<li><p>OBS (What it is and How to Install it)</p></li>
<li><p>Setting up OBS</p>
<ul>
<li>Managing your export settings.</li>
<li>Capturing a PowerPoint Presentation</li>
<li>Capturing your Audio Voice Over</li>
<li>Recording your Presentation</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Recording your Lecture</p></li>
<li><p>Tips for your Presentation</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<p>##<a name="anchor1"></a> OBS (What it is and How to Install it)</p>
<section id="what-is-obs" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-obs">What is OBS?</h3>
<p><strong>O</strong>pen <strong>B</strong>roadcaster <strong>S</strong>oftware (OBS) is a video recording and streaming platform released by the <a href="https://obsproject.com/">OBS Project</a>. Its main software platform, OBS Studio, is incredibly popular among video game players and streamers on Twitch and YouTube. It has a number of bells and whistles that makes it really well-suited for these creators. But, most importantly for our purposes, it allows you to capture a program running on your computer, mix in audio, and export that into a file that you can easily upload to your file/video-hosting site of choice. <br></p>
</section>
<section id="how-to-install-it" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-install-it">How to Install it</h3>
<p>First, go to the <a href="https://obsproject.com/">OBS Project</a> website. Right there on the front of the screen, you should see three links that lead to downloads based off of your computer’s operating software. (You are going to need about 250 MB of free space in order to install it). Click on whichever link matches your system. Once you do that, it should begin downloading your software automatically. From there, install it as you would anything else. (Personally, I recommend just keeping everything at the default installation settings).</p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/1.gif" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p><br></p>
<p>##<a name="anchor2"></a>Setting Up OBS</p>
<p>Once you’ve installed OBS Studio, go ahead and open it like you would a normal program. (If you kept the box checked that read “Open after installation” while you were installing it, the program should do that for you automatically). You should see a screen that looks something like this:</p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/2.PNG" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p><br></p>
<p><a name="anchor3"></a>First thing you’re going to want to do is decide how and where you’re going to export your screen capture. For Windows 10 (my operating system), OBS defaults to using an .mkv recording format and plopping the output into your “videos” folder. That file location may or may not work for you—I’m going to tell you how to change it if doesn’t—but you’re definitely going to need to change the recording format to mp4 (which is more universally accepted on video sharing platforms than mkv).</p>
<p>Look down in the lower right-hand corner and click the <code>Settings</code> button. A new screen should pop up. Look at the left-hand pane and click <code>Output</code>. Go down to the drop-down menu for <code>Recording Format</code> and change it from <code>mkv</code> to <code>mp4</code>. If you want to change where the video will end up on your computer, click on the <code>Browse</code> button that’s in-line with <code>Recording Path</code>. Then just navigate to the file location that you want to export the file to. I’m going to put it where I put the other media I’m using for this blogpost. You can put it wherever you want. (Or, if you’re cool with it exporting to your default videos folder, you don’t have to mess with it at all). <strong>Make sure you hit the <code>Apply</code> button before either clicking <code>OK</code> or exiting the screen.</strong> Otherwise, your settings won’t have saved.<sup>1</sup></p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/3.gif" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p><br></p>
<p><a name="anchor4"></a>Now let’s go ahead and get it capturing a PowerPoint presentation. Open up PowerPoint or your presentation platform of choice. I’m going to be using a <a href="www.libreoffice.org">LibreOffice</a> version of my latest lecture from the Political Behavior class I’m teaching right now. It was originally made in Google Slides, so apologies if it looks a little wonky.</p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/4.PNG" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p>Now that your presentation is open, go back to OBS. Go down to the lower left-hand panel named <code>Sources</code>. Click on the <code>+</code> icon. Start at the top and scroll down to where it says <code>Display Capture</code>. A new window will pop open titled something like “Create/Select Source.” Click <code>OK</code>. The screen should start showing a live view of your computer display. If you use multiple screens, you can go down to <code>Display</code> to set which one you’d like to record. If you have one screen (or, equivalently, if you set your display to be the same screen that OBS is sitting in), you’ll get a pretty trippy look into infinite recursion.<sup>2</sup> <em>Don’t worry. The infinite loop will not be visible during your presentation.</em></p>
<p>Click OK to finish setting up your visual source. (You can click the eye icon in the sources panel to kill the visual feed if you don’t want to look at the recursion while you set everything else up. I’ll do that so you know how and so it won’t be a distraction.) OBS will capture anything that you have on this display. So if you want to capture a Google Slides (or Beamer presentation), simply put your browser window (pdf viewer) on that screen and OBS will capture that. This process allows you to use whatever presentation software you want. If you’re teaching programming or some kind of quantitative methods class, you can even have it display R/Stata/SPSS!<sup>3</sup></p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/5.gif" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p><br></p>
<p><a name="anchor5"></a>Next, we’ll set up your voice-over (that way your students aren’t just watching slides silently slipping by). You have a few options here. Most laptops (and some PCs) have built in microphones. While these aren’t the highest quality, they should do in a pinch. If you have a headset that you use to make Skype calls and the like, that can work as well. Thanks to my YouTubing, I happen to have a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Blue-Snowball-Condenser-Microphone-Cardioid/dp/B014PYGTUQ/ref=pd_sbs_267_img_0/141-4904210-4469436?_encoding=UTF8&amp;pd_rd_i=B014PYGTUQ&amp;pd_rd_r=5869df98-67e3-442d-a8da-1f5b8c3dc437&amp;pd_rd_w=D89NE&amp;pd_rd_wg=KJb7d&amp;pf_rd_p=5cfcfe89-300f-47d2-b1ad-a4e27203a02a&amp;pf_rd_r=R2QY6WQTZKTPYSFCC1DA&amp;psc=1&amp;refRID=R2QY6WQTZKTPYSFCC1DA">Blue Yeti Snowball</a> on hand. (The Snowball is a solid entry-level podcast/vlogging microphone that’s really reasonably priced). In any event, you can go as basic or as fancy as you like. As long as you plug it in and it’s recognized by your computer, you can use it to record your audio.</p>
<p>Once you’ve plugged in your microphone (or headset) of choice, go back down to the <code>Sources</code> panel and click on the <code>+</code> again. This time, stay at the top and click the button that says <code>Audio Input Capture</code>. A new panel will pop open that will say something like “Create/Select Source.” Click <code>OK</code>. A new screen will pop up which will ask you which <code>Device</code> you want to use. If you are using a device (like a headset or dedicated microphone) that isn’t your computer’s default audio input channel, click the drop-down menu and select it by name.</p>
<p>Once you do that, click <code>OK</code>. You’ll now see a new item in the <code>Audio Mixer</code> pannel in the bottom-center of the screen. From here, you can mix the levels of your input channel and your desktop audio by moving the sliders. (If they’re further to the right, the audio from that source will be louder; further to the left and they’ll be softer.) My personal preference is to totally silence the audio coming from the Desktop (I don’t want the video to get random bings from Outlook and distract the viewers).</p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/6.gif" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p><br></p>
<p><a name="anchor6"></a>Now that you’ve got everything set up, you’re ready to record. From here you’ve got a couple of options. If you’re working on just one screen, you’re going to have to minimize OBS during recording so that you avoid the infinite recursion. <em>That’s totally fine. OBS will continue recording after you minimize the program so long as you don’t exit out of it entirely.</em> But you will have the infinite loop for however long it takes for you to click <code>Start Recording</code> and minimize in the beginning <strong>and</strong> to restore the window and click <code>Stop Recording</code> at the end. If you think your students won’t mind—although, I’ll be candid and tell you that they probably will—you could just leave it in. If you have a video editor (like iMovie), you could just chop those bits off and re-export it. Or, my preferred option, you can set it up so that you can minimize the program, press a specific button on your keyboard, and start recording without anyone having to see all the looping.</p>
<p>Go back to the lower-right part of the screen and click on the <code>Settings</code> button again. Go to the left-hand panel and click where it says <code>Hotkeys</code> (second item from the bottom). Go down to where it says <code>Start Recording</code> and click on the field to the right. Your mouse cursor should start blinking. Then press the button on your keyboard that you want to act as the shortcut for your recording command. I’m going to use <code>0</code> on my keyboard’s number pad, but you can use any key that you’d like. I’d just suggest not picking something that you might accidentally hit while presenting!</p>
<p>Once you’ve made your choice, click apply.</p>
<p>##<a name="anchor7"></a>Recording your Presentation</p>
<p>Now that you’ve got all of your settings ready to go, you’re ready to start recording your presentation! If you turned off the infinite loop, click the eye logo again to turn the visual feed back on. Then <em>minimize</em> (not <strong>exit</strong>) out of OBS Studio. Start up your presentation. Then, when you’re ready, press the button on your keyboard that starts your recording. (If you decided not to use the hotkeys, click <code>Start Recording</code> before you minimize out of OBS). Talk clearly into your microphone and make your way through the slides.</p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/8.gif" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p>Once you’ve finished, press the button on your keyboard that stops your recording. Reopen OBS. <strong>DO NOT IMMEDIATELY CLOSE THE PROGRAM.</strong> OBS Studio takes a while to encode your video into an mp4 format. If you close the program while it’s still in progress, you’ll just have a corrupted mess that can’t be opened let alone watched. Personally, I like to have my file viewer open to the directory that I decided to export my video to. It’ll update when the file has finished exporting.</p>
<p align="center">
</p><p><img src="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/9.gif" style="width:75.0%;height:75.0%"></p>
<p></p>
<p>Once you’ve finished the video, you have something that you can upload to your preferred elearning platform (Blackboard or Canvas) or to YouTube. I uploaded a short demo to my personal YouTube (rather than to the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/professorpolitics">Professor Politics channel</a>) where I went through the first couple minutes of the lecture so you guys can see a “final” product.</p>
<p align="center">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/__rKku41JAg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
</p>
<p><br></p>
</section>
<section id="tips-for-your-presentation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tips-for-your-presentation"><a name="anchor8"></a> Tips for Your Presentation</h2>
<p>As I ever-so-slyly referenced in the last paragraph, I’ve been making multimedia content for the web for a while now—pretty close to about 6-7 years. I’m not by any means an unimpeachable expert, but I’ve picked up a few things as I’ve gone along. So I wanted to pass along a few tips for when you’re recording your presentation:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Keep it brief:</strong> Unless you’ve got a helluva radio voice (and an engaging personality to boot), keep your presentation shorter rather than longer. The best video educators on YouTube don’t tend to go much longer than 10-15 minutes—and they’ve usually got some kind of visual animation and music to accompany them. You won’t keep your students’ eyes on the screen for much longer than that. Even if they do, their eyes will be totally glassed over or they’ll have Facebook open in another page. (That may not sound much different than class normally for some, but trust me. It is.) I know that’s frustrating because you probably have a lot more material than that. Trim it down as best you can.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>If you can’t keep it brief, do it in chunks:</strong> If you absolutely cannot cut your material down to below 10-15 minutes, make multiple, shorter videos. Find natural stopping points in your presentation and cut your videos down to about 5-7 minutes. Set up a silent alarm for about 6 minutes that’ll help you wrap it up. This technique won’t let you get away with uploading, like, 10 videos—but you can use it to upload 3-6 that’ll get far better engagement than if you just kept talking for 20-30 uninterrupted minutes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Don’t eat the mic:</strong> watch how close you’re getting to your audio input. You don’t want your lecture to get interrupted by crackles or Darth Vader-esque heavy breathing.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Talk slower. Then talk slower than that:</strong> Some people (like me) are cursed with a rapid cadence. When we talk to people face-to-face, it’s easier to understand us because a lot of our meaning is translated through non-verbal means. But when it’s just you and the slides, fast talking will be the death of comprehension. Plus, if you’re not used to presenting using a microphone, you’re probably nervous about it. Even if you don’t think you’re nervous, you probably are. That’ll bleed over into how quickly you’re going through the material. So if you just finished a video and/or chunk and are thinking “wow, I sure managed to clear through those slides really quickly!”—you’re probably going to have to re-record it if you want students to know what the hell you were actually saying.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Avoid being monotone:</strong> Your students probably understand that this isn’t what you signed-up for; no one’s asking for an Oscar-worthy performance. And unless you’ve got experience with acting, improv, or public speaking, it’ll probably come off as more cringy if you shoot for one. But don’t be like the teacher from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uhiCFdWeQfA"><em>Ferris Bueller’s Day Off</em></a>, droning on about the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act. Try to add some variation in your voice every now and then. Change up your volume, pitch, and tone just as you would if you were speaking before a group.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Don’t strive for perfection:</strong> Don’t try to make this a Ted Talk. Don’t try to make this a YouTube video. Don’t make this into a job talk or conference presentation. Don’t think that you have to have no pauses, no flubs, no imperfections. If you would say “oops, excuse me, what I meant was…” in class, you can say it here. It’s fine. 9 times out of 10, you’ll notice it far more than anyone else will.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Practice before you upload:</strong> Do a couple of short practice runs (1-2 minutes) to make sure you’ve got your pacing, microphone placing, and all-around jitters sorted out before you dive in to the whole thing. As I mentioned, I’ve been doing this for years and I <em>still</em> have to do this. We all do. It’s better to get all the little kinks fixed before you upload your videos and you realize, to your sinking horror, there’s something that makes it utterly unwatchable.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>This is probably going to be a stressful time for both you and your students. This transition (from offline to online) has been abrupt for and it’s having very real consequences on the day-to-day lives of everyone involved. Hopefully, this tutorial will be able to ease that transition, and diminish some of those smaller issues.</em></strong></p>
<p><br><br></p>


</section>
</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Depending on how updated your graphics drivers are, you might also have to change your <code>Encoder</code> settings from <code>Hardware</code> to <code>Software.</code> For what it’s worth, I had to do this—but your mileage will vary.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>As a bonus, you’ll also see the gif capturing software I’m using for this tutorial, LICEcap in action.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I’m choosing to play Switzerland in the immemorial methods war.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{licari2020,
  author = {Peter Licari and Peter Licari},
  title = {Capturing a {PowerPoint/Google} {Slides} {Lecture} with
    {Open} {Source} {Software}},
  date = {2020-03-10},
  url = {www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-licari2020" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Peter Licari, and Peter Licari. 2020. <span>“Capturing a
PowerPoint/Google Slides Lecture with Open Source Software.”</span>
March 10, 2020. <a href="https://www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial">www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>tutorial</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <guid>www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.peterlicari.com/posts/covid-video-lecture-tutorial/images/1.gif" medium="image" type="image/gif"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
