<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing | Peter Licari</title>
    <link>/tag/writing/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Writing</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu7822abfb2f54ce27e2589169adb56259_3245_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/tag/writing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>TIL: Using &#34;tk&#34; as a placeholder when writing</title>
      <link>/til_post/til-using-tk-as-a-placeholder-when-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/til_post/til-using-tk-as-a-placeholder-when-writing/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/til_post/til-using-tk-as-a-placeholder-when-writing/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;tldr-use-tk-in-your-writing-drafts-to-signal-your-future-self-that-something-needs-to-be-replaced.&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;TL;DR: Use “tk” in your writing drafts to signal your future self that something needs to be replaced.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many others, my first drafts for writing projects are a chaotic nightmare that I wouldn’t force even my enemies to read. Interwoven among common grammatical goofs (does anyone &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; know how to use a semicolon) and things that are entirely my own issues to sort out (does anyone &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; know how to spell bureaucracy?) are also a flurry of bracketed reminders for my future self. Stuff like: &lt;strong&gt;[citation here]&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;[author name]&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;[p value]&lt;/strong&gt;, and **[ins However, even after all my re-reads and drafts (including a few read slowly and out loud), a handful will slip invariably slip through and make me feel like a dumb-dumb; even &lt;code&gt;ctrl-F&lt;/code&gt;ing the right or left bracket (“[”) doesn’t help me flush them all out. I know I’m not alone with this either—but I still feel like the dumbest dummy to ever plug away at a keyboard whenever I spy one that’s snuck its way into the “final” draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a trick that I picked up in Tim Ferriss’ &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B01HSMRWNU/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&#34;&gt;Tools of Titans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: Use “tk” as an indicator for your future self and other proof readers that something needs to be replaced. While English can often dissolve into consonant soup (especially by the third re-read), some consonant couplings are less common than others. “t” and “k” happens to be one of the least likely, making it far less likely to ping a false positive when you &lt;code&gt;ctrl+F&lt;/code&gt; it. Also, if you’re working in a word processor (or even in one of many Latex programs and the latest RStudio!), you’ll probably have an instant spell-check feature that’ll put a helpful little squiggle underneath it, which will help draw your attention to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I’ve tweaked the habit to provide a little additional information. Instead of writing just “tk”, I’ll write “tk-cite” or “tk-figure” or “tk-name.” That way, it’s easier for me to remember what exactly I’m supposed to be putting in later. I haven’t been doing this forever but I &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; noticed substantially fewer substitution slip-ups in the brief time that I’ve been doing this in earnest. Hope it helps you too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
